Loyalty Oath Controversy. Collection. 1945-1968. UARC.0393
UCLA Library Special Collections
Loyalty Oath Controversy. Collection.
1945-1968
UCLA Library Special Collections
UCLA University Archives
UARC.0393
5.2 linear feet (13 boxes)
Record Series 393 contains documents regarding the Loyalty Oath Controversy, including a history of the collection, excerpts from Regent's meetings, University related publications, and newspaper clippings.
Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9935214623606533
Historical note
A special file on the loyalty oath controversy was set up in 1951 by Andrew Horn, University Archivist. Since that time printed and manuscript material has been collected dealing directly or indirectly with the University controversy. In 1968 the Caughey Project to study the history of oaths led to an organized enquiry to get petinent materials and papers of people directly involved with the controversy. The responses to the request are included in the collection under "History of Collection." Under the auspices of the same project, Jane White organized and listed the material in the collection. Jane White's list and notes on her work are also includled in the first section of the collection.
In March 1974 the Collection was again reorganized to include the papers of Paul Dodd and others which had since been added to the Collection. The present organization and register attempts to divide the various committees and offices in order to show the inter-relationships that existed at the time of the controversy.
A list of other pertinent background material, and material in the University Archives and the Department of Special Collections dealing with the loyalty oath is available in UCLA University Archives.
Scope and Content
Record Series 393 contains documents regarding the Loyalty Oath Controversy, including a history of the collection, excerpts from Regent's meetings, University related publications, and newspaper clippings.
This is an inactive record series; no additional University records are expected to be added.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online through Calisphere: Loyalty Oath Controversy Collection (100 items)
- History of collection.
  - Andrew Horn, University Archivist; correspondence, notes, etc., 1950. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Robert Vosper, correspondence with Paul Dodd., 1951. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lists of UCB holdings on loyalty oath - Archives and Manuscript Division, Bancroft., 1968. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memos and letters on Caughey Project., 1968. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Caughey Project, responses from request for material., 1968. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Caughey Project, returned letters of request., 1968. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Caughey Project, Jane White's history and list of collection., 1968. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Regents: excerpts of meetings.
  - 1949 Mar 25-Jul 22. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1949 Sep 23-Nov 18. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1950 Jan 04-Feb 24. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1950 Mar 31-Apr 21. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1950 Jun 23-Jul 21. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1950 Aug 25-1951 Oct 19. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Regents: miscellaneous. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Office of the President, Robert G. Sproul.
  - Letters from Sproul., 1950. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Sproul., 1949-1950. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence between Sproul and Paul Dodd., 1950-1952. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Academic Senate: Northern Section.
  - Meetings., 1945 Oct 10-1950 Jun 06. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Meetings., 1950 Sep 26-1951 Dec 05. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Resolutions, etc. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Academic Freedom. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Conference Committee., 1950 Mar 06. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committee of Five., 1950. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Committee of Seven., 1950. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Committee on Financial Assistance. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Academic Senate: Southern Section.
  - Minutes and agendas., 1949 Sep 22-1950 Apr 24. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Resolutions, etc., 1949-1950. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Advisory Committee., 1949. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Committee on Faculty Poll. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Research. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Committee on Privilege and Tenure. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence with Robert G. Sproul. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Conference Committee Resolution., 1950 Mar. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Faculty Steering and Policy Committee. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Steering Committee, Paul Dodd correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Academic Senates.
  - Special Unified Committee on Tenure., 1951-1952. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Special Unified Committee on Tenure, Northern Section., 1951-1952. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Special Unified Committee on Tenure, Southern Section., 1951-1952. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Conference Committee of Deans., 1950.
  - Southern Section - Endorsements of March 01, 1950 Resolution by Departments. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - (South) A-C. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - (South) E-L. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - (South) M-Z. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- UCLA Faculty.
  - Committee for Responsible University Government.
    - Minutes., 1950-1952. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Reports and resolutions. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Jacoby, Neil; correspondence., 1950-1952. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Rolfe, Franklin P.; correspondence., 1950-1952. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Smith, John E.; correspondence., 1950-1952. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Beals, Ralph L.; statements., 1950. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Caughey, John W.; statements. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Dodd, Paul.
    - Statements and speeches. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Notes. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, intra-campus. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with Monroe Deutsch. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with John Hicks. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence with C.L. Mowat. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence from outside the university. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Teletype correspondence with President Sproul's Office. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence concerning Alumni Committee. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with Group for Academic Freedom. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Durrell, Cordell.
    - Statements and speeches. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Notes and resolutions of meetings. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence., 1950-1951. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Griggs, David; notes, etc. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - MacGowan, Kenneth; correspondence., 1950. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - McHenry, Dean E.; statements and proposals. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Popper, Danicel; correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Pucciani, Oreste F; notes and correspondence., 1949-1950. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Roose, Kenneth D.; correspondence., 1949-1950. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Westegaard, Waldemar; speech., 1950 Mar 15. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence A-Z. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Statements, press releases, speeches, etc.; A-Z. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Statements, press releases, speeches, etc. (unknown author). (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Notes and lists on press. (Box 4, Folder 32)
- University of California, miscellaneous.
  - UC, Oath forms and letters. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - UC, Office of Public Information; press releases and letters. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - UC, correspondence from outside the University, A-Z. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - UCLA, Library., 1950. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - UC, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, letters of Roger Revelle, Acting Director., 1950. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Non-Senate academic and administrative employees. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Student groups. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - California Alumni Association. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Non-University materials.
  - Committee for Academic Employees. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Group for Academic Freedom (Berkeley). (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Court cases. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Science and Education. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Phi Beta Kappa. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Librarians. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - American Association of University Professors. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - National Council of the Arts, Science, Professions. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Federation for Repeal of the Levering Act. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Communist Party. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - American Civil Liberties Union. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous and unidentified material. (Box 5, Folder 21)
- University publications. (Box 6)
- Non-University publications. (Box 7)
- Newspaper clippings. (Box 8, Box 9)
- Paul Dodd scrapbook of newspaper clippings re: controversy. (Box 10)
- Beginnings of bibliography on Loyalty Oath controversy, anti-communism, etc. On 4x6 cards. (Box 10)
- Correspondence., 1949-1952. (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
- Poll - correspondence., 1949. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Poll - results., 1949. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Poll - responses from emeriti., 1949. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Poll - responses from professors., 1949. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Poll - responses from professors., 1949. (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Poll - responses from associate professors., 1949. (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
- Poll - responses from associate professors with tenure., 1949. (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Poll - responses from associate professors without tenure., 1949. (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
- Poll - responses from instructors., 1949. (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Poll - responses from unidentified., 1949. (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Poll - responses received too late., 1949. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Newspaper clippings., 1952. (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
- Academic Senate, Southern Section; draft memo re: poll; poll draft; poll & memo (mimeo masters)., 1949 Dec 01. (Box 13, Folder 6)